Guide to the William Jovanovich Papers, 1960-1999
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
William Jovanovich Papers
1960-1999
Jovanovich, William
1.0 cubic feet (1 box)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Personal and professional correspondence with Mary McCarthy, correspondence with McCarthy biographers, typescripts of McCarthy's publications with Harcourt, Brace and Javonovich, newspaper clippings relating to McCarthy and her work, and an audio tape of the 1989 memorial service for McCarthy.
Biographical Note
William Jovanovich was born Vladimir Jovanovich in Colorado 1920, the youngest child of a Polish mother and Montenegrin father, who worked as a coal miner. Educated in Denver elementary schools and the University of Colorado, Jovanovich served in the navy during World War II. In 1943 he married Martha Evelyn Davis, with whom he had three children. Unable to comlete graduate study after the war, he joined the publisher Harcourt Brace and Company as a college textbook salesman. He rose quickly through the company's management ranks. In 1953 he became head of Harcourt's school division and the company's president the following year. Jovanovich presided over the steady expansion of Harcourt, Brace's enterprises, acquiring other publishing firms and even purchasing several theme parks. In 1970, with company shareholders's approval, the firm changed its name to Harcourt, Brace, Jovanovich (HBJ). Under Jovanovich's leadership, the company published several important authors, such as Günter Grass, Umberto Eco, and Italo Calvino. Jovanovich worked direclty with a number of these writers, including Hannah Arendt, Milton Friedman, and Mary McCarthy. Jovanovich and McCarthy first met in 1958, and their professional relationship evolved into a close personal that lasted until McCarthy's death in 1989. Jovanovich continued to play an important role in the management of HBJ until his departure from the company in 1990. In addition working as a publisher, Jovanovich also wrote a number of books, including a memoir, The Temper of the West. Jovanovich died in 2001 at age 81 in San Diego, California.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes personal and professional correspondence with Mary McCarthy, correspondence with McCarthy biographers, typescripts of McCarthy's publications with Harcourt, Brace and Javonovich, newspaper clippings relating to McCarthy and her work, and an audio tape of the 1989 memorial service for McCarthy.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the
Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
Carol Gelderman Papers
Mary McCarthy Papers
Subject Headings
Names:
Arendt, Hannah, 1906-1975; Gelderman, Carol W.; Hellman, Lillian, 1905-1984; Kiernan, Frances; McCarthy, Mary, 1912-1989
Organizations:
Harcourt Brace Javonovich
Subjects:
Politics and literature--United States - 20th century; Publishers and publishing--United States; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974
VCL Categories
Literature and Writing
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, October 2011.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased in 2009 from the Jovanovich Family via Glen Horowitz Bookseller.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1960-1999; bulk 1974-1990; (Folders 1.1-1.20)
  Corespondence concerning a variety of personal and professional matters, including the administration of the estate of McCarthy's friend, philosopher Hannah Arendt, and the resolution of playwright Lillian Hellman's libel suit against McCarthy. Also included is correspondence between Jovanovich and his assistants and McCarthy biographers Carol Gelderman and Frances Kiernan. Arranged chronologically.
- Series II. Mary McCarthy typescripts and Publication Materials, circa 1963-1991; bulk 1986-1991
  This series consists mainly of typescripts of McCarthy's books published by Harcourt Brace Javonovich. These include her autobiography, How I Grew, with her hand-written corrections, and The Mask of State on the Watergate affair. Also included are correspondence and other materials pertaining to the publication of these and other books. Arranged chronologically.
- Series III. Miscellaneous Materials, circa 1975-1990; bulk 1989
  This series consists of materials concerning a gift to Jovanovich from the McCarthy estate and McCarthy's final hospital visits. Also included is McCarthy's remembrance of her friend Nichola Chiaromonte and an audiotape of the memorial service for McCarthy at the Pierpont Morgan Library in New York City in the fall of 1989. Arranged alphabetically.
Container List
- Series I. Correspondence
  - WJ - Mary McCarthy Letters, 1960 (Folder 1.1)
  - Mary McCarthy, 1966-1975 (Folder 1.2)
  - "Mary McCarthy,", 1971-1973 (Folder 1.3)
  - Mary McCarthy - WJ, 1974-1984 (Folder 1.4)
  - Mary McCarthy - WJ, 1974-1979 (Folder 1.5)
  - Mary McCarthy - WJ on H.[annah] A.[rendt] Estate, 1976 (Folder 1.6)
  - WJ gift to M. McCarthy, 1976 (Folder 1.7)
  - WJ - M. McCarthy on Eliz. Y[oung]-B[rühl] biography of H.[annah] A.[rendt], 1977 (Folder 1.8)
  - Mary McCarthy 1982, 1979-1982 (Folder 1.9)
  - McCarthy - WJ: Hellman, etc., 1979-1984 (Folder 1.10)
  - Mary McCarthy - Hannah Arendt, 1981-1982 (Folder 1.11)
  - Carol Gelderman, 1981-1982 (Folder 1.12)
  - Mary McCarthy - WJ, 1981-1983 (Folder 1.13)
  - Mary McCarthy, 1981 (Folder 1.14)
  - Mary McCarthy, 1984-1987 (Folder 1.15)
  - Mary McCarthy, 1984-1989 (Folder 1.16)
  - Mary McCarthy - WJ Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Folder 1.17)
  - Mary McCarthy Papers, 1985 (Folder 1.18)
  - Last Days of Mary McCarthy, 1987-1990 (Folder 1.19)
  - WJ - Frances Kiernan, 1990-1999 (Folder 1.20)
- Series II. Mary McCarthy Typescripts and Publication Materials
  - Stones of Florence Intro. (Blur), circa 1963 (Folder 1.21)
  - Mary McCarthy Mask of State, 1974 (Folder 1.22)
  - Cannibals and Missionaries et al., 1979-1980 (Folder 1.23)
  - Mary McCarthy Cannibals and Missionaries, 1979 February 23 (Folder 1.24)
  - Mary McCarthy Manuscript - An Intellectual Autobiography or How I Grew, 1982 (Folder 1.25)
  - How I Grew - Ms. 1, 1986 (Folder 1.26)
  - How I Grew - Ms. 2, circa 1986 (Folder 1.27)
  - Mary McCarthy - How I Grew, 1986-1988 (Folder 1.28)
  - How I Grew - Vol. I - Mary McCarthy Manuscript, 1989 (Folder 1.29)
  - How I Grew - Vol. I - Ch. 1, circa 1989 (Folder 1.30)
  - Mary McCarthy - 3 Chap. - How I Grew Vol. II, 1991 (Folder 1.31)
  - "Mary McCarthy's Autobiography,", circa 1986-1991 (Folder 1.32)
- Series III. Miscellaneous Materials
  - Gift From Mary McCarthy Estate, 1990 (Folder 1.33)
  - Mary McCarthy - Hospital, 1989 (Folder 1.34)
  - Mary McCarthy Memorial Service, 1989 November 8 (Folder 1.35)
    Audio cassette.
  - Nichola Chiaromonte - Mary McCarthy, circa 1975 (Folder 1.36)